Zalman Yefroikin Papers
Zalman Yefroikin Papers
1902-1968
Yefroikin, S.
5.5 linear feet
Papers of the American educator, author. Yefroikin also used the name S. Efron. Collection includes correspondence, 1912-1966; memorabilia, 1902-1968; and manuscripts, 1920-1968, relating to Yefroikin's writings and to Jewish secular education, particularly the Workmen's Circle schools. Correspondents include Chaim Grade and Melech Ravitch.
148775
Biographical History
Zalman (or Salman) Yefroikin (1893-1966), also known as S. Efron, educator and author, was born April 18, 1893 in Wekshna, Lithuania, the son of Rafaele Yefroikin. In 1921 after his graduation from the Jewish Teachers' Seminary in Riga, Latvia, Mr. Yefroikin emigrated to the United States where he took up residence in New York City. He taught Yiddish literature and Jewish history in the educational system of the Workmen's Circle, a national Jewish labor and fraternal order. He directed its summer camps and later the Workman's Circle High School. From 1953 until his death Mr. Yefroikin was educational director of the eighty-five Jewish secular schools operated by the Workmen's Circle.
Mr. Yefroikin was the author of many textbooks, a contributor to and editor of the Workmen's Circle publication Culture and Education, as well as a frequent contributor to Zukunft, The Call, Der Wecker, Jewish Daily Forward and other.publications. His book on present-day Jewish life in eastern Europe was published in 1965 and translated into English in 1966 as Jews Do Not Surrender.
He was a member of the board of directors of the Institute for Yiddish Research, the executive board of the Congress for Jewish Culture, the executive board of the General Encyclopedia in Yiddish and the administrative committees of the Jewish Labor Committee and the Jewish Daily Forward.
He and his wife, the former Amy Beresin, had two children, Mrs. Vivian Tucker and Dr. Ronald Efron. Yefroikin died in New York City on October 1, 1966. His widow later remarried and became Mrs. B. Fenster.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Zalman Yefroikin Papers are divided into three parts. Most of the material is in Yiddish, but some is in English and a very small amount is in Russian. Correspondence, 1912-1966, includes incoming and outgoing letters arranged chronologically. Significant correspondents include Chaim Grade, author, 1964 and Melech Ravitch, author, 1966. Memorabilia, 1902-1968, includes biographical material, certificates and diplomas, passports, photographs, a conference program, a signature stamp, and a Workmen's Circle camp advertisement. Writings, 1928-1968, includes manuscripts or printed copies of articles, a book, examinations for Teachers' Seminary, a foreword, letters to the editor, notes for speeches and articles, a postscript, quotations from Mr. Yefroikin's works, a report, speeches and remarks, a syllabus, and textbooks, arranged in that order. Individual articles are arranged alphabetically by title. Bound volumes of Culture and Education, each containing more than one article by Mr. Yefroikin, are arranged chronologically at the beginning of the articles category. Textbooks are also arranged alphabetically by title.
The collection includes 29 published volumes scattered throughout the collection:
Vol. 1 One hundred years--modern Yiddish literature, 1965, (Box 2)
Vol. 2 Culture and Education, 1952 (Box 2)
Vol. 3 Culture and Education, 1963 (Box 2)
Vol. 4 Culture and Education, 1964 (Box 2)
Vol. 5 Culture and Education, 1965 (Box 2)
Vol. 6 Bieter Far Yiddisher Dertsiung, June-September 1951, (Box 3)
Vol. 7 The Future, March 1946 (Box 3)
Vol. 8 Convention Journal, April 1937 (Box 4)
Vol. 9 Culture and Education, May 1950 (Box 4)
Vol. 10 Yidn Gibn Zich Nit Unter, 1966 (Box 5)
Vol. 11 Freileche Teg (Box 5)
Vol. 12 Mayn Folk, 1962 (Box 7)
Vol. 13 Fifty years of the Workmen's Circle, 1950 (Box 7)
Vol. 14 Arbeter Ring - its strivings and attainments, 1964, (Box 7)
Vol. 15 Joseph Baskin an the occasion of his seventieth birthday, 1951 (Box 8)
Vol. 16 By the well, 1948 (Box 8)
Vol. 17 Jewish children, 1956 (Box 9)
Vol. 18 Jewish children, 1961 (Box 9)
Vol. 19 Jewish children, 1964 (Box 9)
Vol. 20 The living word, 1954 (Box 9)
Vol. 21 My language book, 1938 (Box 9)
Vol. 22 My language book, 1946 (Box 9)
Vol. 23 My language book, 1948 (Box 10)
Vol. 24 Our word, 1932 (Box 10)
Vol. 25 Our word, 1939 (Box 10)
Vol. 26 A Peretz treasury, 1952 (Box 10)
Vol. 27 A stop forward, 1953 (Box 11)
Vol. 28 The Yiddish word, 1947 (Box 11)
Vol. 29 The Yiddish word, 1965 (Box 11)
Subject and Genre Headings
Grade, Chaim, 1910-1982.; Ravitch, Melech, 1893-1976.; Yefroikin, S.; Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring.; Jewish educators.; Jews -- Education -- United States.; Jews -- Education -- Textbooks.; Books.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Notes (documents); Photoprints.; Speeches (documents); Textbooks.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. B. Fenster, 1968.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1912-1966 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Biographical material, 1921-1968 (Box 1)
  - Certificates and diplomas, 1902-1922 (Box 1)
  - Passports, 1915-1921 (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Mr. Yefroikin, family and friends, 1922-1962 (Box 1)
  - Program of Social Service Department Conference, typescript carbon, May 4, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Signature stamp (Box 1)
  - Vocabulary words, part of textbook, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Workmen's Circle camp advertisement (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Bibliography mentioning Yefroikin articles, One Hundred years--modern Yiddish literature, by Ephim H. Jeshurin (Vol. 1), 1965 (Box 2)
    - In Culture and Education (Vol's 2, 3, 4 and 5), 1962; 1963,; 1964,; 1965 (Box 2)
    - "Around our school," Culture and Education, March 1947 (Box 2)
    - "Assimilation -- factual and disguised," Der Wecker, November 12, 1932 (Box 2)
    - "The Beaten path," Jewish Daily Forward, June 14, 1956 (Box 2)
    - "Beginning of a new road," Our School, ca. 1932 (Box 2)
    - "Blessed be the hands that build," Convention Bulletin (Box 2)
    - "Dr. A. Koralnik and skepticism," Der Wecker, July 1935 (Box 2)
    - "Eastern states conference -- Workmen's Circle schools," Our School, May 1932 (Box 2)
    - "Effect of home enviroment on the child's personality," Our School, January 1932 (Box 2)
    - "Exodus, the book", holograph (Box 2)
    - "Fear in children," Our School, ca. 1932 (Box 3)
    - "Fortieth anniversary of the Folksbiene," Culture and Education, February 1955 (Box 3)
    - "Forty years of Workmen's Circle schools" (Box 3)
    - "The goal of Jewish study," Our School, November 1936 (Box 3)
    - "Greetings on 10th anniversary of Workmen's Circle School," Souvenir Journal, Toronto Workmen's Circle School, April 28, 1929 (Box 3)
    - "Guest of Israel," Jewish News, Tel Aviv, Israel, July 31, 1964 (Box 3)
    - "Heredity and environment," Workmen's Circle School Bulletin, October, 1930 (Box 3)
    - "A holiday of hope," Der Wecker, March 1944 (Box 3)
    - "The ideological path of the Workmen's Circle School," Almanac, galley proof, revised (Box 3)
    - "I. L. Peretz, father of Yiddish literature," The Call, 1952; holograph (Box 3)
    - "The individual and the group in Jewish Life," Workmen's Circle Yearbook (Box 3)
    - "Influences on the development of the child," Our School (Box 3)
    - "Institutions do not clear things up -- they lead us astray," The Future, March 1963; original typescript, revised (Box 3)
    - "Is it proper teaching or is it conservation?" Our School, ca. 1932 (Box 3)
    - "Jealousy and hate, problems of child development," Our School, February 1933 (Box 3)
    - "A Jewish cry of pain," The Future, November 1960 (Box 3)
    - "Jewish education and America," The Future, June 1943 (Box 3)
    - "Jewish education and the Jewish school," Our School, November 1933 (Box 3)
    - "Jewish education at the present moment," Culture and Education, October 1948 (Box 3)
    - "Jewish education in America," The Future, June 1943 (Box 3)
    - "Jewish education in the United States,", 1957; repro. of pr. mat. in General Encyclopedia in Yiddish (Box 3)
    - "Jewish education of our children," The Friend, September 1932 (Box 3)
    - "Jewish life in America", holograph (Box 3)
    - "The Jewish school and the Jewish worker," Der Wecker, February 23, 1929 (Box 3)
    - "Jewish school in American life," Culture and Education, May 1946 (Box 3)
    - "Judaism and socialism in the Workmen's Circle," Der Wecker, May 17, 1930 (Box 3)
    - "Language development in the beginner classes," School and Home, November-December 1930 (Box 3)
    - "Language instruction in our school," School and Home, October 1928 (Box 3)
    - "Let us build again," Our Yearbook, 1954 (Box 3)
    - "Must we make changes in our Workmen's Circle school program?" Culture and Education, January 1941 (Box 3)
    - "Nachum Chanin", holograph (Box 3)
    - "Ninth Workmen's Circle Conference," The Friend, June-July 1935 (Box 3)
    - "Notes: Atlee goes to church," Culture and Education, February 1953 (Box 3)
    - "Our children and America," Culture and Education, March 1951 (Box 3)
    - "Our ideological problems," Culture and Education, January 1956 (Box 3)
    - "Our Youth," Der Freund, October 1940 (Box 3)
    - "Our school problems," Culture and Education, May 1948; October 1958 (Box 3)
    - "Pages for Jewish education -- the Peretz schools of the Workmen's Circle," Bleter Far Yiddisher Dertsiung (Vol. 6), June-September 1951 (Box 3)
    - "Parental pride in achievement of our children," The Friend, June-July 1933 (Box 3)
    - "The path we trod," Culture and Education, May 1944; January 1953 (Box 3)
    - "People in Soviet Russia," Our Voice, May 6, 1959 (Box 3)
    - "Perspectives of the Jewish secular school in America," The Future (Vol. 7), March 1946 (Box 3)
    - "Philip Gelibter", ca. 1935 (Box 4)
    - "The place of our school in Jewish life today," Culture and Education, November 1956 (Box 4)
    - "The positive role of the Workmen's Circle school," Culture and Education, May 1941 (Box 4)
    - "Problems of child education," Our School (Box 4)
    - "Problems of our school movement," Der Wecker, April-May 1932 (Box 4)
    - "Respect for parents," Workmen's Circle School Bulletin, January 1929 (Box 4)
    - "School conference of Workmen's Circle", holograph (Box 4)
    - "A school to unite generations," Jewish Daily Forward, 1968 (Box 4)
    - "The Soviet Union and the Workmen's Circle School," Der Wecker, October 1, 1943 (Box 4)
    - "State, church and federal aid to education," The Future, ca. 1966 (Box 4)
    - "Tenth annual conference of Workmen's Circle schools," Our School (Box 4)
    - "Thirty-five years -- what further?", holograph (Box 4)
    - "To the tenth conference of the Workmen's Circle schools," Convention Journal (Vol. 8), April 1937 (Box 4)
    - "The today and tomorrow of our schools," Culture and Education, May 1953 (Box 4)
    - "Today in Jewish education," Culture and Education (Vol. 9), May 1950 (Box 4)
    - "Trip to Morocco," Jewish Daily Forward, May 1-19, 1965 (Box 4)
    - "Twelfth convention of Workmen's Circle schools", April 25 1941 (Box 4)
    - "A way out," The Friend, December 1943 (Box 4)
    - "What type Jewish education for our children," Our School, ca. 1932 (Box 4)
    - "Why Jewish education?", 1962; holograph, including note (Box 4)
    - "Why Jewish education," The Call, 1962 (Box 4)
    - "Why Jewish schools?" Workmen's Circle School Bulletin, December 1930 (Box 4)
    - "Workmen's Circle school", holograph (Box 4)
    - "Workmen's Circle school annual conference," Jewish Daily Forward, January 22, 1954 (Box 4)
    - "Workmen's Circle school in the light of our times," Der Wecker, November 24, 1934 (Box 4)
    - "Workmen's Circle school survey," Workmen's Circle School Bulletin, October 1929 (Box 4)
    - "Writing and reading Yiddish," Workmen's Circle School Bulletin, April 1929 (Box 4)
    - "World conference for Jewish education," Jewish Daily Forward (Box 4)
    - "The Yiddish schools," The Call, February 1955 (Box 4)
    - "Yiddish secular schools in the United States," Jewish Encyclopedia Handbooks, 1948; repro. of pr. mat. (Box 4)
    - "Yiddish tradition", holograph (Box 4)
    - Unidentified fragments, typescript carbon (Box 4)
  - Books (Box 5)
    - Jews do not surrender, or Yidn Gibn Zich Nit Unter (Box 5)
      Includes the following:
      Original typescript, revised, translated and edited by Theodore Primack and Eugene Kuilman, in English
      Printed copy in Yiddish, 1966 (Vol. 10)
      Book reviews
  - Examinations for Teachers' Seminary, 1962-1963; holograph, typescript (Box 5)
  - Foreward to Freileche Teg by M. Olitsky (Vol. 11) (Box 5)
  - Letters to the editor, Der Tag (Box 5)
  - Notes
    - Articles, holograph (Box 5)
    - Articles or speeches (Box 6)
    - Speech he was delivering when he died, October 1, 1966; holograph (Box 6)
    - Speeches, 1953; holograph (Box 6)
    - Teaching or textbooks, holograph (Box 6)
    - Travel, holograph (Box 6)
    - Yiddish seminar, holograph (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1951-1952; holograph (Box 6)
    - Unidentified, holograph, holograph (Box 7)
  - Postscript in Mayn Folk, by J. Woskowitz (Vol. 12), 1962 (Box 7)
  - Quotations from Fifty years of the Workmen's Circle by J.S. Hertz (Vol. 13), 1950 (Box 7)
  - Report, "World conference of Jewish education in the diaspora", August 12-17, 1962; original typescript, revised (Box 7)
  - Speeches and remarks
    - Holograph; original typescript, revised; typescript carbon, revised, 1957-1966 (Box 7)
    - In Arbeter Ring - Its strivings and attainments (Vol. 14), 1964 (Box 8)
    - In Joseph Baskin on the occasion of his seventieth birthday (Vol. 15), December 1951 (Box 8)
  - Syllabus for Workmen's Circle Sunday Schools (Box 8)
  - Textbooks
    - By the well, anthology of literature, ed. with Zalman Kazdan (Vol. 16), 1948 (Box 8)
    - Jewish children, with Yudel Mark (Vol. 17, 18, 19), 1956; 1961,; 1964 (Box 9)
    - The living word, with Chaim Bass (Vol. 20), 1954 (Box 9)
    - My language book, with Chaim Bass, 1st edition (Vol. 21, 22); 3rd edition (Vol. 23), 1938; 1946,; 1948 (Box 9, 10)
    - Our word, literary anthology, ed with H. Besprovsvany (Chaim Bass) (Vol. 24, 25), 1932; 1939 (Box 10)
    - A Peretz treasury (Vol. 26), 1952 (Box 10)
    - Book reviews, 1952 (Box 10)
    - A step forward, with Yudel Mark (Vol. 27), 1953 (Box 11)
    - The Yiddish word, with Chaim Bass (Vol. 28, Vol. 29), 1947; 1965 (Box 11)